all right welcome everyone to this
week's foreign seminar this week we've
got Zach Stein who's going to talk to us
about stuff in his new book that is just
come out take it away
thank you John so thanks thank you for
having me here you know it's a sacs I'm
very excited I haven't spoken about my
book yet so so a few words about me
before I get going so let's see I am
what's sometimes called a high achieving
dyslexic which means that it's not a
coincidence I'm a theorist of education
and so I went to Hampshire College which
is a unique school and then the Harvard
University Graduate School of Education
where I worked with kurt fischer and
howard gardner kathryn Elgon along the
way i co-founded with dr. theo linda
Dawson
Latika which is a nonprofit that's
dedicated to using the new sciences of
learning and especially developmental
psychology to re design testing
infrastructures very broadly in the k-12
system and in the realm of adult
assessment so recently I've stepped back
from luck teeka and have been writing
and doing consulting work and I'm now a
scholar here at the road and Institute
and so this book I'm going to talk about
is my second book my first book was my
dissertation which was published by
Routledge under the title social justice
and standardized testing and I focus on
John Rawls his theory of justice and the
history of standardized testing so I
kind of look backwards in that book this
book I'll share my screen now so this
book's that's coming out probably late
summer early fall putting the final
final touches on of course as a dyslexic
the hardest part is the final part and
so my wife is Megan is a very skilled
copy either there and so she and I've
been going over the final proofs of it
and so she'll be out soon and like I
said my previous book looked backwards
and this book is looking for
this is in some ways a book of
educational futurism but it is also a
book that calls for really radical
changes in the way we think about
education and theorized education so
what I'm gonna do is I'm going to walk
through the key themes of the book and
kind of give an overview of the book
pausing in some places to elaborate what
I think are important details and yeah
so that'll be that'll be the plan so
this is the best way to actually frame
the book and this was drawn on a napkin
for me by a colleague and basically it's
the structure of educational crisis and
this happens both for individuals and
collectives which is to say any time the
task demands of what you have to do
outstrip your actual capabilities you're
in the learning crisis you need to
transform or fail or change what you're
trying to do and so this I think is one
way to characterize what's happening on
the whole for our culture in this
historical moment we are facing a
educational crisis of unprecedented
proportion and it's trickling down into
the life world of everyone and that
means that many individuals are
themselves in a situation of educational
crisis and of course those people most
in that situation aren't the young
people the people who are actually in
school and so what I'm arguing is that
unless we don't unless unless we change
schools very radically unless there are
major changes to the spare structure of
schooling those young people now being
socialized into our society will not be
able to meet the task demands made of
them in order to reproduce the social
system so it's a strong argument so you
notice these learning curves and then
you look at these data and so the key
chapter one of the first check the first
chapter in the book is health education
and Anthony and
it allows me to make this broad argument
where I can contextualise education in
the context of global crisis global
meta-crisis so these come from some work
that's being done on the Anthropocene
and the Anthropocene has to do with the
melding and forever now inextricably
bound relationship between the biosphere
and even some of the you know geological
features of the earth and humans and so
what you're seeing here socio-economic
trends which are mirrored by earth
system trends and what this means is
that and you'll see all of these are
quasi hockey-stick type things and this
is um exactly back to the first figure
which shows well ya to task demands of
what it means to live in society and the
task demands of sustaining human
civilization are becoming more complex
you know each one of these gr systems
and each one of these key socio-economic
trends is turning into a problem to be
solved
it's but better so what I do in the
preface to the book because it's a
collection of essays what I do in the
preface of the book is weave together
these essays with a set of themes and so
this is the only text heavy slide which
I'm gonna kind of read to you in my
whole deck but it's worth getting these
themes direct and clear so the book
talks about as I've already done putting
education in the context of a global
meta-crisis and by meta-crisis what I
mean is that it's not it's not one
crisis it's actually a crisis of crises
it's a crisis that has to do with the
confluence of many other crises so in
that context I'm saying that that
traditional approaches to thinking about
educational systems which have depended
on human capital theory are now obsolete
if they were ever really good so it's a
strong critique of especially reductive
human capital theory which I'll talk
about later as a way of thinking about
the function of Education Society so I'm
pointing out the interdependence between
educational organizations the teach
early practices that occur in them and
the rest of society culture kind of
related to that is the potentially
revolutionary impact of computer
technologies on educational practice so
I think these things speak for
themselves it is the culture and society
and the technological basis on which
education takes place as we go from the
chalkboard to the flatscreen right from
the chalkboard to the smart board we're
we're changing the nature of teach early
practice in a very fundamental way so
that's that's key so part of that
transformation of teach early practice
has to do with the transformation of the
nature of teach early Authority and this
is a particular kind of effort kind of
it's the flourishing of certain post
modernist views which question authority
period and I'm saying that obviously
there's pathological forms of authority
like there are pathological forms of
Authority and yet there are very
important forms of authority like teach
really Authority and parental authority
which should not be used pejoratively
but should be actually researched into
their structure so one of the things I
do in this book is look at the structure
of teaching the authority from the
perspective of cognitive science and
developmental psychology and philosophy
so and then related to this issue has to
do with what our teachers allowed to
talk about and as the meta crisis
deepens and the existential issues get
more complex that humanity faces I'm
saying that we're gonna actually need to
revisit the role of religiosity and
spirituality as an aspect of human
development and education and I'll talk
about that more and then what kind of
ties it all together is the need to
engage in some serious out-of-the-box
thinking which is to say some concrete
utopian theorizing adjacent futures near
adjacent futures which are not a matter
of resources but a matter of political
will and imagination and so much of what
I lay out here could be seen as utopian
especially my vision for a kind of
self-organizing educational hub network
to replace our big
dinosaur schools bunch of micro schools
that are all related and I also lay out
13 social miracles which I see is the
condition for the possibility of actual
schooling so these are things like basic
income guarantees and you know
guarantees of life continuation of the
biosphere for example needs to be
assured if we want to educate in any
kind of sincere way a generation that's
going to reside in the future and so yes
I'm speculating but the point here is
that in times of crisis and in times of
rapid transformation there needs to be a
sense of what's possible not just what's
bad about what's going on but what we
can do next so one of the things that
holds the book together is my work in
meta theory and so meta theory is a kind
of super discipline and it is often
characterized as part of the emergence
of the meta modern phase of cultural
development and so that's a mouthful and
so a minute modernism and post-modernism
and the question of how many prefixes we
can afix them to modern is a good one
but the meta modern is unique and the
meta modern is a structure of feeling
that emerges after post-modernism
so the meta modern doesn't just seek to
fragment and multiply perspectives and
subjectivity
the meta modern seeks to actually
reintegrate those perspectives that have
been fragmented if the modern takes a
singular perspective and the postmodern
takes all possible perspectives the meta
modern steps tend to organize all of
those perspectives usually in some kind
of hierarchy or some kind of set of
comprehensive categories if you're doing
meta theory in a meta modern way now
there are meta modern forms of
aesthetics meta modern literature etc
XANA murder it's emerging I believe and
I think it's useful to think about
this here are the four quadrants of ken
wilber integral meta theory which is one
of several meta theories that I used
throughout the book I find his to be
particularly clear and so what you're
seeing here is a kind of checklist to
assure epistemological comprehensiveness
for interdisciplinary investigation
which is to say that if you're doing an
investigation into something that's very
complicated like education you want to
make sure that you're covering all your
bases and not just looking at it through
one particular set of perspectives right
so this is the postmodern insight that
you don't want to take one perspective
certainly not the perspective that's
been dominant and oppressive for so long
you want to take many many many
perspectives what this does is organize
perspectives and it says there are
disciplines and perspectives that deal
with the subject so for example this
would be the experience of the student
in the classroom this is the upper left
quadrant so there's the experience of
the first-person experience of a student
which can't be neglected
now the first-person experience of the
student is related to the physiology of
that student the neuro chemistry
especially stress hormones in schools
right so what the student experiences as
internally anxiety has a neurochemical
mirror or relation which could also be
investigated right similarly in the
lower right-hand quadrant you could look
at the student entirely from the
perspective of the school system and all
of the forms of measurement that encode
the student within the infrastructure of
the bureaucracy and the school buses and
the roads in the actual building all
stuff that is about the systems of
Education and then there's the culture
the lower left quadrant which has to do
with the interiors of the collective
right not just the experience of the
student but what's the culture of the
school so in each of these four
quadrants there's whole branches of
educational theory and neuroscience and
things that are sold not educational
theory but as someone who does deep
educational theory actually everything's
related to education and
so yeah so that's integral Metta theory
which I use alongside several other men
theories including the dialectical
critical realism of Roy Bhaskar and a
couple others so that's worth thinking
about not part of Metta theory
especially in to Romed a theory is this
is one of the things that allows us to
get beyond human capital theory and so
it's important to recognize that human
capital theory is basically theorized
into the lower right quadrant in
Wilbur's diagram right human capital
theories says that the function of
education is to produce workers
basically I mean this is like a terrible
simplification but that's at the end of
the day of I was explaining it to a
middle schooler I'd say that that's a
human capital theory so that the skills
and capacities that are developed within
schools are ultimately to be fed into
the economic system and the marker of a
successful school system is one that can
act effectively and efficiently populate
the roles within the economy with the
appropriate skills and subjectivities
and dispositions that were fostered
during school and so what that means as
we measure educational success by the
degree to which education raises to the
GDP so if you want a really simplified
well notice I'm mentoring the metric
here a lot of kids are measured in
school we measure educational
effectiveness at the level of the school
and the level of the country in terms of
numbers and measures this is going to be
a theme that is woven throughout the
book and a theme in my meta theoretical
investigations in general have to do
with measurement and measurement
technologies something I'll return to so
but when human capital Theory did was
allowed for the triumph of objective
measurement in education and the
emergence of what I called the education
commodity proposition which is the idea
that the best way to understand
education is as a commodity and the
education commodity propositions similar
to film the labor commodity proposition
which argues that labourers come on and
what that does is it reduces theorizing
about education
is to say the education commodity
proposition has us thinking about things
like return on investment in education
right as this thinking about quantifying
in terms of finances and a structure of
you know flows of people as being
related so that's one of the things that
I argue against is the use of
standardized testing to encode the
education commodity proposition on to
the subjectivity of a student so that
there are financial consequences for how
they do on the SAT it's true so yes so
one of the things that the whole book is
trying to do is to say we gotta shake
loose from thinking about education as
being entirely wedded to the economy and
started thinking about education very
differently in part because the economy
is gonna be very different ten years
from that so but I'm getting out of the
story
okay so that was meta modern metatheory
which is part of the book but I also do
a lot of theorize in human development
and trying to bring together several
different models of learning and several
different models of you know the way the
human develops over time these
developmental models let's say that neo
Piaget didn't work and this is a quote
that frames a section heading of the
book and characterizes in many ways you
know my view of what's wrong with
educational psychology you know despite
the dominance of cognitive science that
for the past couple decades the evidence
has not suggested that the mind is
computer like if you look at it what
it's suggesting is actually that the
mind is it's doing the opposite of a
computer the mind is much more like an
ecosystem which is my preferred metaphor
for the mind so but the way we measure
the mind and the way we talk about the
mind has been deeply affected by the
metaphor of the mind as a computer so
you'll remember that Freud changed
history by using the metaphor of a of a
steam engine right which was the one of
the key technologies
of his day that the psyche has energy
the energy builds up it needs to be
released this kind of psychodynamic
theory was about this basic metaphor of
steam so the metaphor of the computer
has been very dominant so and again it
reflects our obsession with the most
sophisticated technology and and
anthropometry take it and encode it onto
the subjectivity of the people in that
culture who are run by that technology
and so you know when you're looking at
the mind as computer metaphor and if you
look at it carefully image the table in
my book where I compare the mind as
computer metaphor with the mind that's
ecosystem metaphor and what's striking
is that the mind is computer metaphors
that's really bad like it so for example
if you're not a good learner it means
you've got broken hardware right it
means is that you can accurately
characterize its total power of someone
with a single number IQ similar to the
kind of computing power a computer you
know it also has you thinking about
teachers as repair people or factory
workers that are dealing with a complex
or rather a complicated object that kind
of can be fixed or updated in a
mechanical way so I'm trying to steer us
away from that metaphor and towards a
metaphor we think of the mind as this
organic it's very complex evolving
organism or set of organisms so the mind
is the ecosystem metaphor allows us to
think of the mind as metabolizing this
environment and as having within its
self internal complexity that can create
growth and it also means that the
metaphor changes and the teachers no
longer a repair person or a factory
worker the teacher is now much more like
a gardener or someone who tends to the
maintenance of ecosystems it also means
that each student is unique as opposed
to a computer metaphor where if you're
not like this kid there's something
wrong with your hardware you know by
definition huge ecosystem is different
from each other
system and you should expect that and
leverage that so when you think about
the mind is when you go system you get
that advantage and there's a whole whole
list of so I'm doing deep theory in
human development and I worked from a
developmental model that is based on
from the work of my adviser Kurt Fisher
and it's an EOP is yet Ian's model and
what this tells us I'm not gonna rehash
the whole thing what it tells us is that
there are very different qualitatively
distinct capacities that emerge over the
course of the lifespan and we need to
respect the internal working of the
organic development of the mind and not
impose upon it what we wish it was as if
it was a computer that we did software
update instead we need to be able to
track growth patterns and what Kurt did
along with some other colleagues was to
apply dynamic systems modeling
techniques as used in biology to track
the development of psychological
capacities across these levels and Kurt
demonstrated very clearly that what you
see in growth it's not the stereotyped
Pease Union ladder of growth but in fact
what you see in growth is a very dynamic
third by kind of like rhythmic up and
down with bifurcations and nonlinear
jumps and other dynamics that reveal in
mind to be not mechanical in lockstep
but in fact fluid contextualise and
changing moment to moment up and down
the skill scale right so I don't want to
linger too long on the learning theory
but there's a lot to say so along that
skill scale which is the far left here
there have been other researchers who
have looked at how various domains of
capacity on the fold and become more
abstract and complex so from the from
the top to the bottom here this reads
from early childhood through very mature
highly educated and again what we're
looking for our school systems that
don't put a ceiling on people's
development
right so for example a nationalistic
school system will not allow for the
emergence of level six moral reasoning
right a nationalistic school system
especially one that's national
ethnocentric is going to constrain the
reflective ability of adolescents
intentionally to keep them thinking
below a universal universalistic moral
view right so that the power of these
developmental models is that they allow
us to give aspirations and to critique
you know those things which inhibit the
full flourishing of these capacities
which are mapped out this is a map of
human potential is one way to think
about it so I use maps like these to
characterize some of what needs to take
place when we're thinking about
education reform and then this last one
is very interesting in terms of the
ecosystem metaphor and the best way to
characterize the mind as dynamic so this
is basically a very complex
representation of a psychotherapeutic
dyad that has basically a hundred and
eighteen conversational turns you can
see if they're along the bottom axis and
what it's tracking is both the
developmental level which is the gray
upper line and then the conceptual
content which is the black lower line
alright so what we're seeing here is
that the number of concepts varies the
black line goes up and down the
complexity or difficulty of working with
those concepts berries that the person
is moving between very complicated forms
of reasoning and simpler forms of
reasoning in the same conversation and
then the beads along the string at the
top like the black and and white kind of
diamonds these are emotional coatings so
what they did it was videotaped and they
were able to code the emotional dynamics
and you'll see that the emotional
salience and the effect present in the
conversation varies with the complexity
of the conversation and the total
conceptual
load of the conversation so what this is
is like it's like it's like a time
capture of kind of the natural behavior
of learning which is nothing like a
simple pet in ladder and also nothing
like a computer that simply gets a
download what we're looking at is the
sciences of learning telling us that our
schools are broken the sciences of
learning are telling us that each kid in
the classroom is gonna have such a
complex and unique experience that we
either constrain that or we leverage
that this is the sum of my messaging in
the book has to do with listen this is
not this is not just political right the
the mind works in a certain way as the
body works in a certain way so there are
things that work and do not work with
regards to the human body in terms of
healing illness similarly there is a
reality to the structure of the mind and
how it works and education has long
neglected to take account of this if we
continue to ignore the sciences of
learning then as I said we will have a
whole generation that is unable to meet
the task demands that are going to be
put upon by the global meta-crisis so
the meta theory the human development
work that frames rethinking about
education in general and then I move
through several chapters where I look at
various aspects of the issues so one of
the most important themes in the book
has to do with the extinction of the
large school system with centralized
factor like buildings and the
obsolescence of that factory model so
this is a picture of Russo's amino and
this is supposedly the only book that
got comped to miss his daily walk when
when Immanuel Kant got his copy of
irzu's Emile he would sit on a tree they
just sat and read it and that's because
it was it was it was taking
the basic structure of education out of
institution and looking at the most kind
of primordial dynamic between teacher
and student and it was also thinking
about in a post conventional way how can
education be something that brings the
child to society eventually it's not you
like that that child can then change
society as opposed to fitting in and so
of course in the 70s the great theorist
Paul Ilic wrote a book called D
schooling society and similarly to this
in this vision of Rousseau is what
you're looking at is this radically
individualized education without school
without schools and a traditional sense
without walls right where the whole city
is a school and the child gets basically
the equivalent of educational credit
card and they can redeem it for time
with elders this is alleges visions very
interesting but it was written before
the internet and before the emergence of
both the postmodern and the meta modern
kind of structures of feeling and theory
and so what I do in this book is to kind
of an integral Redux of the d.school
mood and suggest a network of Education
hubs and so that was written about and
you've blurred that John circulated it's
an excerpt of my book that's been online
for a while now and you know to
summarize the idea is that I'm arguing
that we should literally dismantle the
insides of most of our existing schools
and replace the basic infrastructure
with something that looks more like a
combination of a daycare a co-working
Center a library a museum that a
computer out and what this means is that
it's going to be a hub where the
community organizes using all kinds of
resources which I specify in the book
when community organizes around the
engine the intergenerational
transmission of knowledge right so that
instead of having a school in
traditional sense you have hub
with very different sets of norms about
what counts as education and there are
different ways of tracking and measuring
students moving through it and of
organizing pop-up classrooms and of
having tutorials and of having working
groups of kids at different ages and so
what you're looking at is what I call
the the kind of 21st century one-room
schoolhouse put all the youth together
and put all the resources of adults
together you can call it a school if you
want to but it doesn't look like a
school anymore especially when it's
facilitated by very sophisticated
technological infrastructure which
allows for tracking each student all the
learning opportunities available
basically a complex time and skill
sharing network so that's one of the
visions that I lay out I also do some
basic thinking in theoretical metrology
and probably the core chapter of the
book has to do with what I call the
global crisis of measurement and it
became clear to me as a theorist of
education that one of the main things
distorting the educational system has to
do with the way that we measure it and
think about measuring it and then I
started looking around and realized that
wow a lot of the problems that we're
facing globally have to do with the way
we measure things and think about
measuring them GDP is a great example
the gross domestic product is still
widely used as a index of economic
health for policy decision making and
yet it's been known for and argued by
economists even mainstream economists
that you know in essence we're we're
looking at a simplification that may be
more damaging than useful as opposed to
something like the Gini coefficient
which actually represents inequality
within the economy not just the total
growth but the distribution of economic
productivity and reward Gini coefficient
right so as an example and there's
literally hundreds and I discussed many
of them in this chapter where the basic
measurement infrastructure setting the
wrong set of constraints and mapping
reality in the wrong way and having a
measurement structure that doesn't
or come from an infrastructure that is
distorted creates what Bhaskar calls
Demi realities small versions of
something that's there you're tracking
something but you don't know what it is
and it's actually worse you know it's
worse than flying blind because if
you're flying with instruments that you
think you can trust but you can't so so
that's that's important and then towards
the end of the book I lay out a series
of social miracles and as I've already
mentioned these are conditions for the
possibility of real education and they
include really radical suggestions about
how we could change the nature of
society in order to allow for a
different way of fostering
intergenerational transmission which is
to say a different form of Education
would result if we for example thought
about the world boy but mr. fuller did
beyond the traditional boundaries of
nation-states one of the things I argue
for in the book is a redrawing of the
borders and a rethinking of the nature
of nationality as part of fostering a
cosmopolitan educational edge you know
initiative and so that the social
miracles chapter is the most utopian but
I think it also shows the the real
challenge in the clearest way of over
faced with a basic income guarantee for
example is characterized as an economic
issue but the basic income guarantee is
fundamentally an educational issue
making that transition and the results
of that transmission the transition
rather you know making that transition
would be probably one of the greatest
educational challenges we faced when you
have a generation who didn't have it and
then a generation that does and then of
course disentangling education from the
need to become a wage laborer
disentangling the definition of what it
means to be human from what it means to
be a wage laborer right these things are
emerging and again I'm saying towards
the end of the book that or actually
need to revisit the way we think about
what it means to be human you know the
answer
is a significant enough marker of the
uniqueness of humanities power in the
universe which is to say the power to
changed the nature of a whole planet and
so we need to take that seriously and
it's also also worth noting that you
know one of the most kind of generative
and long-lasting radically alternative
educational systems was the Waldorf
School and the Waller school model is
revered by people who don't even think
have a religious thought it works but
it's worth noting that it was founded
and all of the founding learning theory
and all the educational structures and
even the architecture of those buildings
is from a merging religious worldview of
Rudolf Steiner which incidentally had to
do a lot with life and the meaning of
death and so this Alex gray painting
shows that especially again as the
global crisis demons and things get more
complicated and the numbers of people
who are subject to geopolitical violence
or ecological catastrophe increases then
we're gonna have to deal with some moral
conversations in the public sphere and
with our children and so yes we're gonna
need to start thinking about what to say
in response to the deepest questions
that can be asked by the youth and right
now we're very inarticulate and one of
the reasons there's been a resurgence of
neoconservative neo reactionary thought
and even the resurgence of ethno
nationalist sentiments has to do with
the inability of
some of the most educated to make
sincere and profound responses to
deepest questions that can be asked so
that's kind of the broadest overview of
the book and you know from what I just
said it seems like half of this book
possibly have been written and it took a
long time to write but as a result of it
being so much in it
I think it's gonna be exciting when it
comes out and just to see what happens
so I will stop and stop sharing my
screen and take questions so thanks
everyone for listening
[Music]
Oh